Hello and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrdan.
And today we're gonna be looking at
isotopes and more specifically, we're
gonna learn how to write isotopes and
how to solve percent abundance and
atomic mass problems, which you will
most likely see in your first semester
of general chemistry on a as a homework
problem or, or as an exam problem.
So we definitely wanna make sure we
master that to get all the points
that we can to pass chemistry.
Now, what exactly is an isotope?
Well, for all kinds of different atoms
that are out there, if you go to the
periodic table, you'll see that every
one of them has an atomic mass, but they
have a bunch of decimals behind them.
So what an isotope is, is atoms that
are the same element, but they have
different atomic masses, meaning that when
we have all these individual isotopes,
they have different numbers of neutrons.
So, which can be really confusing
for a first time student and maybe
it still doesn't make a lot of sense.
So let's try to, let me try to
explain this to you so that way
you are able to follow along.
The basic idea behind it is sort
of similar to this example here.
So right here I have three different pies.
They are actually all the same
exact pie, but I changed their
size, meaning I changed their mass.
So if I have a pie and I look at
this, my first pie is the little one.
He weighs about a hundred
atomic mass units.
Great.
And then my next one weighs
150 atomic mass units.
It's still the same pie,
but it's just bigger.
That is all.
Now if I have another
one, it's heavier as well.
200 atomic mass units, but
they're all the same exact pie.
They are just different sizes.
Atoms that are different.
Isotopes are like the same thing.
So whenever they have a different
number of neutrons, so kind of referring
to more the right hand pie, right?
So this one has more neutrons.
This one over here on the
left has less neutrons.
It's a similar idea.
So just by adding more neutrons
or less, the mass is going to
go up and down as a result.
Now being that there is a different amount
of these that exist in our world, right?
We have all kinds of different size
of pie, different size elements.
There is a certain percentage of
them that exist, and based on that
is how those average masses exist.
So let's try to dive into this and
see if we can understand this world of
isotopes, just like the pie example.
Because life is a big slice of pie, and
we're gonna try to understand it, right?
So let's get into it.
All right, so back to
where we were at before.
The thing about the take home message
from our example was that isotopes
always have the same number of protons,
meaning they are the exact same element.
So like before, they were the exact
same type of pie, the same element
will have the same number of protons,
but their masses will change.
So whenever we see this, more neutrons
means more mass, which is a heavier atom.
Whenever we have a lighter atom that
is less mass and if fewer neutrons.
So more is heavier, less
is is lighter and fewer.
So whenever we're looking at the periodic
table, let's say if you look at carbon,
for example, like I have here, well,
the atomic mass is included in the
information found on the periodic table.
However, this value here
is a average, right?
So what we are seeing here is that 12.009
is an av, it taught is an average mass.
So when we are looking at
all these, it's an average.
It does not completely and accurately
show each individual isotope.
It's an average of all of them, or a
weighted average of each individual one.
In fact, carbon, carbon has multiple
isotopes, and let's try to get
into this to be able to see exactly
what this is going to look like.
Every single isotope of an element
is identified by the mass number.
Meaning that the mass number is equal
to the atomic number plus neutrons.
Now, why is that?
Well, if you remember from your,
from your chemistry class or from my
previous videos, the atomic number
is equal to the number of protons and
being that protons and neutrons are
the heaviest component within inside
of the nucleus, this is what rules are.
Atomic mass.
They both equal approximately
1.00 amu or one atomic mass
unit, both that and neutrons.
So what we do is the format that we,
that we write, all this looks a little
bit like this, where we write the
mass number in the top left corner.
We write the, um, the atomic
number in the, in the bottom
left, the charge in the right.
And you might see it very
much written like this.
The atomic mass is
written by the letter A.
The atomic number is
written by the letter Z.
You have your element symbol and
then your charge, which if there,
if there is an ion form of it,
so either a cat ion or an anion.
Let's do an example of how this will look.
Let's go back to our carbon example.
So if we had carbon right there, like
earlier I mentioned there's multiple
isotopes, there's three of them.
Let's practice writing all three.
So if I have carbon, right, so
we write down our element, right?
Which is this letter C.
The first thing you gotta do
is what is your atomic number?
So when you look at your periodic
table, you'll quickly see and from
the what was up from above that,
the number for that was six, right?
So we have a atomic number of six.
Now being that I mentioned that
we have three different isotopes,
we're gonna write all three of 'em.
Now, the thing that's important here
is even though they're all different
isotopes, and notice how they're
slightly increasing in size, is that
they all have the same number of protons,
which is the most important part.
They have the same number, protons.
Now the next part is your mass.
So for for carbon, there's
carbon 12, carbon 13.
And Carbon 14, which is
referring to their masses.
So when we write these, we can
write carbon 12, 13, and 14.
Now, what exactly does this tell us?
Well, when we look at that, if
you remember, the atomic mass is
equal to protons plus neutrons.
Um, also when you have your atomic
number, this is equal to the protons.
So protons, in this case, a six.
This is your protons plus neutrons,
so you can kind of do some little
simple algebra to be able to tell
you how many neutrons are there.
So for example, for carbon 12,
we have six neutrons for carbon.
Uh, 13 we have seven.
And for carbon 14 we have eight neutrons.
So it progressively gets a little
bit heavier as we go from the
left side to the right side.
So it gets heavier 'cause
of that extra one neutron.
It's like our slice the pie.
As the pie got bigger, it got heavier.
Same thing with carbon.
We're adding an extra neutron
each time and most of the time
isotopes just differ by one to two.
Uh, two neutrons.
It's usually not a huge difference.
But they could have an extremely
different effect on how they
behave within the world around us.
Um, by adding more neutrons, it could make
it less stable, possibly radioactive, or
could even have beneficial effects that we
can find all around in our everyday lives.
So, for example, a fun example of isotopes
is in your, uh, smoke alarms at home.
A lot of them have americium 241.
Which is americium 241 and it's uh, it's
a slightly radioactive compound, but
once smoke kind of changes that little
radioactive compound inside, it actually
was what's gonna set up your smoke alarm.
So it's nothing that's harmful to you, but
it's just kind of a cool thing to see that
there's an ice to being used even in your
own house, whether you realize it or not.
Um, some other different
examples too, of this.
Let's say if I want to write oxygen 14
ion, this is another way that you can
illustrate how ions are written as well.
So not only do we have that, uh, notation
of the atomic nu, the atomic mass with
the number, and then our element with the
charge, but you can also write oxygen 14.
Help illustrate that, oh,
this is still an isotope.
So let's get at it.
Let's try to write in that format
that we had earlier, and being
that this is an ion, well, we
gotta think of our pure rock table.
Oxygen is a non-metal, meaning that
it has a tendency to take electrons.
So this is an anion.
Or if you think onion, 'cause
it makes you cry, right?
It makes you sad.
So that would be our anion
example over here, right?
So now going off of that, so
how would we go and write this?
Well, same as before,
we'd write our symbol.
That we were, it was given
to us that this is oxygen 14.
Right?
So we'll write that down.
And now we gotta look up
what the atomic number is.
So when you look on a periodic
table, you'll quickly see
that oxygen is number eight.
Now, what is the charge tenancy for this?
Well, if you kind of think about how
your periodic table is, this is, um,
two columns from the far right side.
So what that is, or sorry, three
columns from the far right.
Fluorine's column is negative one.
Oxygen is in negative two,
nitrogen is negative three.
So what this is gonna tell us that
this has a tendency to make a negative
two charge for our problem here.
And that's how you can do an ion, right?
We can show the charge in this
case, and that's the big difference.
Let's go on to some more fun examples.
Okay.
Another really kind of cool example
is that isotopes are all around us.
Even the simplest atom hydrogen
has three different isotopes, which
are commonly seen all around, and
actually all three of 'em have their
own unique names to determine them in
more of like a physics world or even
sometimes in organic chemistry too.
Protium is the top one, which is our
normal hydrogen that we use every day.
Uh, we have deuterium, which
is very often used in organic
chemistry, or tritium is also used.
Now.
What is the difference?
Well, with each of these, right?
If you think of a first hydrogen, that's
just one proton, zero neutrons, and we're
even showing that with our bore model
by showing just one proton in there.
Then for deuterium, well, we have
one proton, and now one neutron.
Which is being shown in blue inside
of our little bore atom here.
So there's our little neutron, and then
with tritium, which is a little more
unstable, we have one proton in two
neutrons with inside of our nucleus.
So the only thing that's
changing is your number neutrons.
They're all hydrogen, every single
one of them being that the protons are
what determined that this is hydrogen.
The only thing changing is
its mass and the number of.
Neutrons here.
So you can still see that these two, when
we add 'em together, are equal to one,
that the one and one are equal to two, and
then the one plus two are equal to three.
So we still have that simple mathematics
here of how those masses are about.
Let's go on to percent abundances to be
able to solve this next type of problem.
Okay.
Now, like earlier that I mentioned,
atomic masses are an average.
Of each of the individual
isotopes that make up an element.
So whenever we read our periodic
table table, for example, with
carbon, right, the number that
was on the periodic table table is
12.009, which is a weighted average
of carbon 12, carbon 13, carbon 14.
So that is how these numbers are found.
What we used to find it is
a, is the formula that's up
here that's in the green box.
Which is atomic mass is equal
to the relative abundance
of each individual isotope.
So what exactly does that mean?
What is a relative abundance or
written with the letter F here?
So relative abundance is a percent.
Meaning, oh, we gotta
remember our percents.
And if that's something that you haven't
quite mastered, please refer to my
math skills to ace chemistry video on
percents, which goes over all the key
tips on how to use percents in chemistry.
Um, but the simple part of it really
is, is that all we are gonna do
is for the percent, is we take our
number and divide it by a hundred,
which will put it into decimal form.
We'll use that number and we'll multiply
it by the mass of its respective element.
So you're always given the percent and
the, the actual mass for that isotope.
We take all those values.
And we add it to all, to the abundance
and the mass of the next isotope.
And we keep going until infinity,
until we run out of isotopes.
It's a general idea on how to use this.
So let's try and look at a specific
example of how we can do this
and what it kind of looks like.
So in a problem like this, this one says,
calculate the atomic mass of magnesium.
Given the natural abundances
n mass of each isotope below.
So for a lot of these types of
homework and exam problems, you're
given a list of all the isotopes,
which have the masses for each one.
So we can see we have
magnesium, 24, 25, 26, right?
And we have a mass for each
individual one, and then they
also have their percent abundance.
Now, keep in mind, This
is a weighted average.
So what that means is it's very
similar to how your grades are
calculated in your classes.
So for example, maybe in your
class, 25% of the grade is homework.
Maybe 10% is the final, 30% is an exam.
But each one of them has so many
points allotted to those categories.
However, it can't go over
that specific percent.
It is weighted right for your final grade.
It's kind of a similar idea here.
Every single category has a percentage
that goes with it, and we add up all
the points, which is murder masses.
So let's try to do this using our formula.
Now, my big tip here is we
gotta convert each of the the
percentages to decimal form.
Okay?
So our first step is what we're
going to do is start plugging in our
values into our equation, and then
convert things into percents as we go.
So we have our atomic mass, which is going
to be equal to each individual isotope.
So for the first part, we have our
first line, which is at which I'll do
in purple to match sort of the colors.
So we have 23.985, which is our
mass, and then we'll multiply that
by the decimal of our percent.
So we're just dividing.
78.70.
Buy 100 to get it into that decimal form.
So that would be number one.
So this is isotope one, or we can
even label it as isotope MG 24.
Now what we're gonna do is do the
next one, which is isotope Mg-25 and
plug that into the equation as well.
So we'll take 24.985.
Multiply that by 0.1013, which is
our percent, once again converted.
And then we will close our parentheses,
add that to the next isotope.
So the line will continue down here.
And once again, we'll take that
relative abundance times our mass.
So we have the mass of 25.982.
We're just doing this third line here,
and then we'll multiply that by 0.1117.
And that's what, how we'll do that.
And just as a reminder, the only
the way that we got this number is
11 point 17 divided by a hundred.
So that's percent to decimal's
how these numbers are coming up.
So we'll take these numbers when you
are putting them in your calculator.
Make sure you are using percents
for each individual part.
So that, or sorry, not percent.
So you use, uh, parentheses for
each individual part so that
way it gets added up correctly.
You don't want the order of
operations to get accidentally, uh,
crisscross and messed up by accident.
Always use parentheses.
So when you do that, your final
answer is going to be 24.31 amu.
And you'll see that it actually matches
very closely to what you will find on
your periodic table, which is also 24.3.
Um, keep in mind this number's gonna
be slightly off 'cause there are a
lot of other isotopes that do exist
within whether, uh, radioactive or
there are unstable in nature as well.
So there's actually dozens of isotopes.
Do a Google search on isotopes
and magnesium and you'll see a
big list of them that do exist.
There are a lot of them.
Onto another type of example that you
might see with natural abundances.
So with some other types of examples,
sometimes you're given problems that don't
quite have all the piece of information.
However, they might be
easier than you realize.
So for this one, it says bromine
occurs in nature, mainly in
the form of two isotopes.
It says 79.
Bromine has a natural abundance of 49.7%.
Calculate the abundance of bromine 81.
Okay, so how are we
supposed to do this problem?
It doesn't give us like
the actual numbers of mass.
We could try to add it up and solve
backwards using our periodic table.
However, there's a much easier
way of thinking about this.
So being that there are two isotopes, what
is the total percentage of all isotopes?
So think about that.
What could be your possible total
maximum grading in the class?
100%.
Right.
So being that it's a hundred percent
is the total, well in this case
we have two individual isotopes.
One of them is 49.7%, and we
don't know what the other one is.
So is there an easy way to go
about and try to solve this?
And the answer is quite frankly, yes.
Just subtract the percents.
So if you move things around right, and
we make it where it's a hundred percent
minus 49.7%, it will equal our percentage,
uh, that is representative of bromine.
So a hundred minus 49.7, and
what you will get is 50.3%.
This is a, an extremely common problem
that is put on exams, on homeworks, in
chemistry classes all around the country,
and the number of students that overthink
it thinking they have to use the equation,
they have to plug all these things in.
Read the problem carefully,
write what's given to you and
notice what is given to you.
Sometimes it's just simply writing
out your full percentage, right?
'cause it should equal a hundred percent.
What are all your pieces?
If this problem wasn't, if it already
gave you both percents, you could
still go through and solve it.
Like the one we did above where
we put it into, into our equation.
Just like before, right?
It would just, it would be one
less isotope, so it'd be a little
easier than the one we did earlier.
I hope that this video helped and
there'll be more videos to come
throughout the coming months and to help
you with, with chemistry, and I look
forward to seeing you all next time.
Please hit that like and
subscribe button to help support
the channel, keep it growing.
It's been growing a lot.
I appreciate all of you and thank you
all and have a wonderful day by now.